To take us through sort of a high level of your response, and then I'm sure
there'll be questions from the committee.
Do you also just want to take a minute to introduce yourselves?
Yes. We do have a board member who wished to
dial in via Zoom. That's Erik Westergaard,
our acting chair.
Great. We will make sure that we get him in as soon as we can, if
he's there.
He is here.
Oh.
Oh, excellent.
Accept the promotion to the panel, Erik, and then we'll see your face.
But do you want to kick us off while that happens in the background?
Sure. I think Erik was going to
give you a bit of an opening statement, but I can introduce myself-
Great
... and my colleagues if that's helpful.
Do that.
So I'm Tim Sparks. I'm the general manager of Networks and System
Change at the Authority.
We have Grant Benvenuti, who is the manager of
Network Policy at the Authority, and we have Nikolai Mumford,
who is one of our senior legal counsel.
Erik, can you hear me now?
Great.
I'll give him a minute.
Okay. Can everybody hear me?
We can hear you.
My apologies.
Hello, I'm Erik Westergaard. Unlike
Tim,
I'm the deputy chair. We have recently had
a new
chair appointed to the Authority.
I'd like to make an apology for our new chair not being able to attend.
He started today, and he's currently undertaking his
Electricity Authority induction.
You have our written evidence and our update.
I'll take those documents as read.
As a starter, I thought I'd be useful to provide some opening
remarks about the Authority's Electricity Industry
Participation Code and the Authority.
The Electricity Industry Act sets out the framework for the industry,
for industry governance, and it includes establishing
the Authority as an independent rule-making body, the scope of
its rule-making powers, and the processes the Authority must
follow when making or amending the Electricity Industry
Participation Code, the rules of the electricity industry.
Since it was established in 2010, the
Authority has focused on maintaining existing and making new
rules necessary to operate the largest and most
complex machine in New Zealand.
We're doing this at a time of unprecedented change in the energy
sector, and it's through these rules that we meet our main
objective to promote competition, reliability, and the
efficient operation of the electricity industry for the long-term
benefit of consumers.
More recently, the Authority was given the additional objective of protecting
the interests of domestic and small business consumers in relation
to the supply of electricity.
Mr Miller has made five complaints about different provisions
of the code under various standing orders.
In summary, Mr Miller thinks the code could be better in several
areas. We agree. His complaint is that the code's
inadequacy rises to the level of a
breach of standing orders. We disagree for the reasons we
set out in our written submissions.
The code needs to be kept under review and updated in response to
new and changing technologies and business models.
The Authority is consistently vigilant for opportunities to
amend the code so it better promotes achievement of our main
objective and the interests of consumers.
When the Authority identifies a part of the code that no longer best
promotes those outcomes, we act to amend it in a
transparent and timely manner.
To amend the code, the Authority is generally required to consult
and to assess the costs and benefits of proposed amendments.
Many of the matters Mr Miller complains about are already being considered
through the statutory process updating the code.
Consultations are public, and we would welcome the submissions
from Mr Miller on any of our code amendment proposals.
And we don't make these code changes alone.
To aid the Authority in amending the code, the act requires the
Authority to
establish the Security and Reliability Council and at
least one advisory group. Currently, the Authority
has six industry working groups in operation.
In the last two and a half years, the Authority has made 52
code changes.
And I note that this is more changes than in the previous five
years. The pace of these changes reflects the changing
nature of the industry.
The Authority prioritizes its work based on the
benefits of any amendment relative to others.
This prioritization applies to the issues raised by Mr Miller,
and we have set out in our written submission some of the work the
Authority is currently doing in this area.
While we might have thoughts on the policy positions Mr Miller
advocates for, until we have done work to develop a
policy, including any related code amendments
and consulted on it, we cannot be certain that the policy is the
right one. We consider the regulatory framework and the act
enables the Authority to address the policy issues
raised by Mr Miller's complaint. That's all I have to say
in opening, and we're open to questions from the committee.
For convenience, I will ask my fellow
Authority team members to lead those questions.
I will contribute as necessary. Thank you.
Thank you, Erik. Thank you.
Oh, there are a few questions. Some of them are specific,
but I just want to clarify at the beginning.
So is the EA's contention that there is no public law
jurisdiction for the Regulations Review Committee to consider your
regulations?
I
wouldn't go so far to say there's no public law jurisdiction, but
possibly.
Some of the things that he's making complaints about are clearly things that have
been made directly by Parliament.
Schedule 6,
part 6A of the code, for example, was inserted directly into our code
by Parliament. So I guess that raises a question
about what would the jurisdiction of the Regulations Review Committee be to
scrutinize that. We're not ruling out that you couldn't scrutinize it.
I think it's just difficult to make
that argument, that that scrutiny would
lend itself to protecting Parliament's interest in ensuring
those regulations represent what its
intention was.
Does that make sense?
Yep. So
you
say Eric's submission is consistent with
the Regulations Review Committee being able to consider a complaint about your
roles.
Rather than making a jurisdictional argument by saying the committee can't look at
these things, I think we'd rather say, if you are looking at them, take into
account that Parliament very intentionally placed
some of these provisions into the code and relatively recently.
So not much time has gone by and the circumstances haven't changed so much.
Yeah.
And the authority has taken steps to update those provisions where it
has seen it necessary in the short term.
Let's ask about some of those changes then.
So, one of the first was the barriers to entry to
small scale generation, and the response from EA was helpful on this
point.
I just want to understand,
it's somewhere where you've pointed to as a matter of policy that EA is continuing
to work on.
How will we know? What are the
points in the review timeline for that for EA?
If
other consumers have
this same experience,
how does Parliament account to them that those
changes are happening, and at what points?
Thanks, Chair.
Yeah, that's a very good question.
All our
work program's public.
We've just published this today, I think our
updated statement of performance expectations for the coming year that has our
current work program in it.
As far as the work for small
scale
distributed generation goes,
that's contained within a program of work we call our networks connections
program. That's been running for about two years now.
There's already been a significant number of changes,
and the last one was in May,
which was the export changes to the export limits that raised those export limits.
We're currently working on
the next piece of that puzzle, which is
around some minor clarifications to our policy intent
and looking at balcony solar, which is obviously
a topic of interest. And we
don't talk publicly much about that,
about any of those changes, before we get ready to
release the paper. And the reason for that is staff are still developing
what our proposals are going to be.
And until our board, who is the authority, until the board make the
decision to consult,
the board can change those at any time.
So we do
socialize what we're working on,
but not the content of that until we're ready to release consultation
papers. So the next one's in about September.
We're intending to go to the late August board meeting with that one, and that's
the balcony solar one. And then there's another one which will intending to
be just before the end of the calendar year, which looks
at the
detailed process itself for
mainly residential consumers with rooftop solar,
how the process they go through to apply and get that connected.
So that is the next big piece, once we get this little stuff
through the
mill.
Just to add to that, I think it's important to
remember that the authority is the expert body that Parliament has put in place
to essentially determine what priorities should be given to
what
changes need to be made to electricity industry or the participation code.
We have, as we mentioned, consultations are generally public.
Our work program is public. We are always open to
submissions, including from
Mr Miller, about what we should be focusing on,
and we take any of those kinds of submissions seriously.
But ultimately,
we are accountable to Parliament.
Yes.
We've been appointed. Yes.
Yeah. Miles Emerson.
Thanks, Chair.
The new rule allowing
distributors
to
allow exports of at least 10 kilowatts at individual connection points,
unless this would compromise network reliability or safety.
How are you tracking that? How do you track the percentage of
rejections, just
so you're getting an idea of whether the
networks are being overly cautious or
maybe
putting some barriers in place to stop those
connections being connected to the
grid?
Thanks. Thanks, Chair.
That change came into force, I think, on the 12th-
11th of May
... 11th of May, yeah. Yeah. So it's only just come in.
Just prior to Christmas,
so nine months ago,
we required all distributors to give us
a whole lot of data on their connection processes, including things like
processing time frames, declines, and that sort of thing.
And the intention is for us to use that.
We're still going through the analysis of that data. It's a massive piece of data.
Yeah.
We're going to use that as a baseline.
We are intending to go back out and refresh that data just
around Christmas time to get the next 12 months' worth,
and then we'll put a permanent monitoring regime in place
to collect data regularly from distributors on that.
In the last
two months, so I think 11th of May, 11th of June, 11th of July, so just
over two months it's been in force.
It seems to be going okay. We have had inquiries
from consumers about whether distributors are correctly applying the
rules,
and we've talked to two different distributors about how they apply the rules.
So we do think it is going okay and that
generally, consumers are getting the 10
kilowatts if they want it, because 10 kilowatts is
quite a large installation. So not all
consumers can afford or have the roof space for-
No
... 10 kilowatts, yeah.
There's quite a few that are-
That are
... outside between 10 and 15, isn't there?
Yeah.
We've only got time for two more questions.
One will be from Joseph Mooney and one will be-
Thank you, Madam Chair. I would interestingly, the hedge contracts or
the non-discrimination obligations
which you've recently brought in, I think 1st of July this year,
to try and ensure that, well, particularly for
the large generator retailers don't fail their own requirements.
As I understand it, available in four pricing reimbursement contracts.
I know you've got the six-month
assessment that I think that you put in place to monitor this.
I'm just wondering, is this the mechanism that you are intending
to use to ensure that these are working, or do you have
another process that you intend to use to ensure these NDOs are working
as intended?
Can we take that one offline and come back to you on that?
Sure.
I think we probably don't have the detail on that, unless
Eric, you have a comment to make on that, I think we'll take it offline
and come back to you if there's time.
That's fine.
That would be great.
Just a final question on the
part of the complaint which relates to lines companies accessing batteries.
The rules have changed.
This is one where there's been a longer runway, so you might be able to provide us
with longer insight into whether the core of the
policy problem is that some lines companies can use batteries as a
tool to build
to capacity more efficiently,
build to peak more efficiently,
but that there might be anti-competitive
offshoots of allowing them to do that at scale.
Is that something where the rules have,
rule changes, in your view, have led to greater
distribution of batteries amongst the lines networks?
Thanks, Chair. I can answer that one, too.
Okay. There is no restriction or
barrier on distributors owning batteries or any of the
generation themselves. What there is a threshold-
Yeah
... above which, which is 50 megawatts, which is actually quite large.
Above that threshold, if they want to do that, then they have to put some
protections in place, what we call the arms' length rules, to ensure that
any competitor has a
reasonable access to be a competitor to their own
internal divisions.
The rules were under Part 3 of the Electricity Act, and they recently moved
into the code. We have the power
to grant exemptions, and we had it under the Act, and
we still have that power under the code as well.
And we have granted exemptions to two lines companies, distributors-
Yeah
... to own more than that 50 megawatt threshold
without having to put the arms' length rules in place.
And the underlying reasons for those, they'll be in our published
exemption decisions, but the underlying reasons for those is that the benefit
of the arms' length rules was outweighed by the cost.
Yeah.
So we granted those exemptions. And those powers work well, and
any distributor
can apply for an exemption, and they always get assessed on a case by case.
There's no precedent effect. Every one's assessed on its merits.
And it's a sort of first in, first served as well then because that is precedent
setting, so you might have competitors who want to build in Auckland, but they're
competing with Line Vector's battery.
Yeah. Any competitor that wants to
install in Auckland-
Yeah
... doesn't have to apply to us.
Yeah.
Okay? It's only the-
They have to get the connection agreement.
And that is, we've made some pretty big
changes to the code, in December last year-
Yeah
... around those very large connections.
Anything above
300 megawatts, I think. There's some
very large changes to make it easier and fairer for those
competitors to apply, both
more transparency against other competitors as well, so they can all see what's
going on, including the distributor's own
generation arm if they want to own. And of course, Vector doesn't.
Vector's one of the ones that
their generation's well below the threshold.
That's great.
Yeah.
Thank you very much. That's all we have time for.
Really have appreciated you coming in.
And thank you very much, Eric, and
warm wishes to your chair in his new role.
Thank you. And
pass on the invitation, if you want any further information from
the Authority at any time, please reach out.
We're happy to provide that to you and to help you.
Thank you.
Have a great day. Thank you.
I think that's pretty on time, as far as I can see.
We have 15 minutes with you.
Yeah.
I'm sure there will be questions.
But in my experience, the best way that these hearings work is if you spend a
little bit of time talking about not only your written complaint, but
also why this is motivating-
Yeah
... for you and what you see as the appropriate remedy.
And then we'll open up for members on both sides to ask you a couple of questions
before the end.
Okay. All right. I have written something to just keep myself to time.
Great.
Tena koutou katoa, Madam Chair and members of the committee.
Thank you for allowing me to come and speak today.
I just want to first acknowledge the clerk's advice that the committee can only
consider the secondary legislation that has been made.
So I've narrowed the submission down to just the foundation curriculum
policy statements around English and mathematics and statistics under
Section 90 of the Education Training Act.
So this narrowed submission goes to grounds A and H of the complaint
under the standing order.
Parliament delegated curriculum-making authority to the minister under Section
90 of the Education and Training Act.
Section 4 of the act states its purposes include establishing and
regulating an education system that is high quality, culturally
responsive, seamless, and inclusive, and that honors Te Tiriti of
Waitangi and supports Māori-Crown relationships.
My submission is that a delegated legislative power of this kind is normally
expected, I would say, to be exercised in a way that is transparent and
traceable through the documentary record so that Parliament and this committee
can verify that it's been exercised consistently with that statutory
purpose.
The documentary record, which I know I've sent you a bunch of bits of,
contains a number of curriculum development documents, design principles,
design criteria, consultation records, curriculum development processes,
and then the final curriculum statements.
The curriculum development record includes different curriculum architectures at
different stages. Those include the Understand Know Do,
Themes Knowledge Skills, the UKD Progress Outcomes, and then the
final Strands Knowledge Practice structure that was used in the final document.
The documentary record also shows different treatments of Te Tiriti of Waitangi by
cultural foundations, inclusion and equity across the successive
curriculum development document.
Development record further shows agreed design principles, criteria, writing
groups, quality assurance processes, error review, and other revision
process. My submission is that this documentary pathway connecting these
elements to the final curriculum statements made under Section 90 is not
readily apparent from the record itself.
Mm.
The question I guess I'm posing to the committee is whether the documentary
record demonstrates that this delegated power has been exercised
transparently and in a manner that can be traced through the record.
And that's the standard I'm asking the committee to apply under grounds A and H of
the complaint.
Cool. Okay.
Dr. Jun Nan, do you have a question?
I do, but Chair, do you have a question?
Yeah, I just-
Sure.
To start, Dr. Coleman, I wanted to ask you, this is an
area that I am an expert in.
Yep.
And so in the development of the sort of two-phase
development where you've got the first being the year zero to six
English, the zero to six Te Reo Rangatira, year zero to
eight Mathematics and Statistics, and then the second
phase-
Yeah
... which was the public consultation.
Are they both
problematic? Is it all problematic, or is the issue that the
purpose statement
was given a different sort of effect in
particularly the language curriculum statements?
I'm
trying to understand which parts the committee
will be best spending its time on
understanding, the parts of the complaint that relate to
the purpose that was initially made by Parliament.
I think in terms of the
... Let's check in terms of which part of it.
I would say it's all problematic-
Okay
... honestly. Yeah.
Yeah.
I think
you would struggle to see how Te Tiriti of Waitangi, for
example, has been
embedded and
is apparent throughout the draft curriculum.
Well, not the draft
now, the English curriculum and maths curriculum documents.
And that's something that's been commented by other
... PBTA and NZED have both lodged submissions around those things.
Yeah. Okay. And as we pass through
it,
comparing this to, say, the last time that curriculum statements would have been
made, what's a useful way of
comparing Parliament's purpose being given effect
in a curriculum statement in the past?
Hmm.
I don't know, honestly.
I guess the through line that you can see from the purpose of what
Parliament exercises into that initial foreword into the
curriculum statement-
Yeah
... I suppose from 2007, and then how that's been carried through the
learning areas themselves.
Okay.
Yeah.
Really helpful. Thank you.
Okay.
Dr. Jun Nan.
Yeah. Thank you, Chair.
I guess one of the things, if you're looking at Section 90,
which is the empowering position of the curriculum, is
that Section 90 is quite broad. It does give ministers a lot of actual
genuine powers to kind of do, any ministers, to do all of those things.
But one of the things that whatever happens within the
Education Training Act that must be fulfilled is around purpose of the act.
Mm-hmm.
So we're looking at holding it up to Section 4.
As you will know that there are different parts, strands to that
purpose.
You mentioned in terms of inclusion and Te Tiriti aspect-
Mm
... which are both the two explicit mentioned aspects of the purpose of the
Education and Training Act. Do you find-
This is a broader question, but you have more specific questions around the extra
supplementary documents that you sent.
Do you find that the way that the framework and the
curriculum design has happened actually meets the standard that one would
expect of the Ministry of Education,
or potentially the government, the Crown, when it comes to
the purpose of the Education and Training Act around Te Tiriti
inclusion being the first part of my question.
I guess the second part with that, following on from what the chair
was asking, is how has previous
curriculum designs, if you know,
have done things differently to try and meet that standard as expected of the
purpose, and that this one, in that sense, doesn't quite meet that
standard?
Okay, so I guess the question one is, do I think that it's met the standard of
inclusion and equity? And I guess my answer would be no , I don't think it
has. And again, that comes down to the lack
of visibility of the principles around Te
Tiriti o Waitangi throughout the learning area.
So not just mentioned in the purpose statement.
I'm talking now about the curriculum document for the learning area of English, for
example.
Yes.
But actually how that's carried through into the detail, through the knowledge and
practices and all of the different phases of the learning.
Similarly,
and this is in those documents I submitted around the two clearing
design principles,
I guess the mention of inclusion and what inclusion
meant, going from a recognition of diversity
to a more sort of standardized all children
encompassing definition.
And just a follow-up question.
So in relation to the supplementary document that you've submitted,
can I just check? So there are two
design principles.
Yeah.
One on the 19th, I believe.
And one on the 30th. Which is less than two weeks apart.
Yeah.
But the two are quite different.
Yes.
This might be quite a simple question.
No.
Why are they so different?
Okay. So I couldn't answer that question for you.
I can tell you how I got these documents, and therefore
that might help. These
documents are both labeled the 12th of April 2024.
The publicly released version, which is the 19th of
April version,
I had seen whilst I was working at the Ministry of Education, and that was a
document that we were given to say this is the new design principles
upon which we will be now developing our work.
I was the lead writer for the arts curriculum.
The 30th of April version
is also dated the 12th of April.
Mm.
Is the same number document, but was signed on the 30th of April.
It is quite different.
The first time I saw that was two weeks ago.
It was sent to me as a result of a request for
material around the consultation of the
current drafts of arts, technology, social sciences, and sciences and learning
languages.
I was asking about the consultation process, and I had asked around,
what would you be assessing the feedback against?
The first response I got
mentioned a few things, and it gave me the establishing a knowledge rich curriculum
cabinet paper. It did say, "We are also going to hold them against the
design criteria." I went back and said, "And what are they?" And they sent me this
document.
Oh, okay. I understand.
So it doesn't make sense to me in terms of the timeline,
but that's how they came to-- Yeah .
Okay. I understand.
And so then just trying to understand,
so that was then public consultation follows, and
then later
it gets to October '25, which is when the minister's then making a decision
about those. So presumably,
within that time period,
you've gone back and--
Well, the Ministry of Education's been able to go back, consider public
feedback, and then there are more changes, and then it comes to the
minister to make that decision, all enabled by
Parliament's-
Yeah
... passing a reading of the-
Yeah. So I guess
my understanding of that procedure normally-- Well, we did some consultation around
the draft work that I was doing in 2023, and that similarly had a
process for going. We put some stuff out for consultation, just
our initial things with the arts, technology, and science.
NZCER as a research entity, collated
that consultation material, wrote a report.
The report came to us.
Recommendations came to us. We kind of looked at them, didn't negotiate, decided
what we were going to respond to, and then responded to that.
I don't know
what was done with the consultation material from the English.
We
probably have time for one or two more questions.
I was going to say, I do have follow-up
questions.
Me too. I just had a single question.
Sure.
So,
I'm just
trying to parse out, and from your documents it was really helpful, but just as a
global view-
Yeah
...
Crown's got to exercise a degree of deference to Te Tiriti o
Waitangi-
Yeah
... as our constitutional document.
At what points were there checks that that was happening?
Like the decision-making steps, so they give rise to the judicial review, but we're
not really concerned with that. We're concerned with
whether Parliament's intent, which should be read alongside Te Tiriti o Waitangi's
effect, is
part of the purpose.
Is there a built-in part of the process?
So I would suggest that, while I was there,
in terms of the documents that we were creating during 2023 around curriculum, we
had,
yes, there was an Oraru Taki group, and there was-
... considerable kind of checks with, we had a Māori advisory
within the ministry and an inclusion advisory within the ministry that
would look at what we were doing and consider it from a
disability standpoint, from a languaging standpoint, and then, as I said, there was
a specific Māori group that would look at it.
I don't know about this particular piece of work, whether or not
that happened.
Okay.
What I can say is that the version that we saw
of the design principles, the 19th version that had
a note to Te Tiriti and bicultural foundation is quite typical of
something we would have in the Ministry of Education, and a document that didn't
have that would've been out of step.
Out of step. Okay, gotcha. Understand. Dr. Junnan.
Yeah, I think I'm still stuck on the fact that you got two documents that's dated
at the same day, and I'm assuming one of them is the one that's gone to
possibly the
minister, because I can see the minister has made comments on that particular
document. But the other one's the one that stayed with the ministry.
Would that be-
Yeah.
Is that normal?
No.
Is that normal that-
No. And as I said, I had not seen the document with the
minister's handwritten notes on it, I only saw two and a
half weeks ago or whenever it was sent to me.
And the reason I guess was slightly taken aback is I
thought, I've seen this date of this document before, I've seen the
title of this document before, I've seen the number of this document before,
but it looks very different.
And so no, it was not given to us inside the
ministry
while I was there.
Gotcha. Cool.
While you were developing the curriculum?
Yes.
Okay, cool.
Okay.
We've run out of time for questions.
That's okay.
But really, really appreciate you coming in.
Thank you so much for making yourself available.
If there's any other things that come to mind, feel free to just give
us a short written follow-up.
Okay.
Awesome. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Thank you, Dr. Coleman.
Okay.